Finding Aid for Institute for Global Education records, 1971-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute for Global Education records 1971-2008
Institute for Global Education.
5 linear feet
2009019 Bj 2
Grand Rapids nonprofit organization working to achieve peace and social justice through education and outreach; records include administrative files, clippings, correspondence, event materials, publications, photographs and scrapbooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Institute for Global Education (donor no. 10131 ) in November and December 2008.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The nonprofit Institute for Global Education (IGE) was originally incorporated in 1971 as the Michigan Institute for Nonviolence. In 1977, it became the Michigan Institute for Global Education (MIGE) and its center of operations shifted from Ann Arbor to Grand Rapids. During this time, many of its members were concurrently involved with the American Friends Service Committee. When the Western Michigan office of the American Friends closed in 1980, MIGE assumed its peace and social justice work and shortly thereafter dropped "Michigan" from its name.
Throughout its history (and over the course of its iterations) IGE has striven to "think globally and act locally" by working with churches, schools, and a wide range of activist groups to fight racism, sexism, economic exploitation, and nuclear proliferation. Internal working groups have focused extensively on violence and oppression in Central America, South Africa, and the Middle East among other places. Since 1980, IGE has spread its message of peace through the publication of the "Equity" newsletter and the sponsorship of seminars, workshops, peace festivals, and a wide range of community events. A host of committees and affiliated groups have allowed IGE to expand its educational and outreach activities to the Grand Rapids community and beyond.
The Institute for Global Education records illustrate how community organizations coalesce, expand, and evolve to become agents of positive change. It will be of interest to persons researching social movements in Michigan and abroad from the 1970s through 2008. The record group consists of six series: Administrative and Related Records, Events, Publications, Affiliated Groups and Committees, Photographs, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
American Friends Service Committee.; Creative Responses to Conflict (Organization); Global Resources Committee.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Institute for Global Education.; Michigan Institute for Non-Violence.; Nonviolence--Michigan.; Peace movements--Michigan--Grand Rapids--Societies, etc.; Peace--Study and teaching--Michigan--Grand Rapids.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bergman, Walter, 1899-; Demonstrations--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Institute for Global Education.; Peace.; Wagbo Peace Center (East Jordan, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Administrative and Related Records
  The Administrative and Related Records series documents IGE's background and general administration and includes bylaws, clippings, correspondence, financial records, grant proposals, and information related to meetings and volunteers.
  - Background and History 1981-1997 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1977-1996 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1977-2004 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1978-2002 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records 2002-2005 (Box 1)
  - Grant Proposals 1981-2005 (Box 1)
  - Meetings: Agendas, Minutes, and Reports 1978-2005 (Box 1)
  - Volunteer Time Sheets 1997-2004 (Box 1)
- Events
  The Events series documents seminars, workshops, conferences, speakers, marches, performances, and festivals sponsored by IGE to promote its message of peace and social justice.
  - Benefit Concert for Humanity 1983-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bourgeois, Roy (lecture) 1981 (Box 1)
  - "Christopher Columbus Follies" 1992 (Box 1)
  - Eastown International Work Camp 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Economics as if People Mattered" (retreat seminar) 1981 (Box 1)
  - Esquival, Adolfo Perez (lecture) 1986 (Box 1)
  - Great Peace March for Global Nuclear Disarmament 1986 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Peace March for Global Nuclear Disarmament 1987 (Box 1)
  - "Mothers and Others" 1988 (Box 1)
  - Multi-Cultural Global Perspective Conference 1986 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - Peace Fest undated, 1997-2005
    - undated (Box 1)
    - 1997-2001 (Box 1)
    - 2002 (Box 1)
    - 2003 (Box 1)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 1)
  - "A Peasant from El Salvador" 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Soviets, Meet Middle America" 1988 (Box 1)
  - Student International Issues Seminar 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - Travel Seminar to Honduras, Nicaragua, and El Salvador 1986 (Box 1)
  - Witness for Peace Delegation 1990 (Box 1)
  - Youth Leadership Conference 2000 (Box 1)
  - Youth Leadership Conference 2001 (Box 1)
  - Other IGE Events 1975-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series documents material published by IGE, including a near complete run of its newsletter, "Equity," from 1980 to 2008. Other materials include special bulletins and "Justicemakers," a profile of peace activists in the Grand Rapids area.
  - "Equity" (newsletter) 1980-2004 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1999 (Box 2)
    - 2000-2008 (Box 2)
  - "Justicemakers" 2004 (Box 2)
  - Special Bulletins 1984-2002 (Box 2)
- Affiliated Groups and Committees
  The Affiliated Groups and Committees series documents previous iterations of IGE, working groups, special committees, and external organizations that have partnered with IGE. Particularly well-documented groups include the American Friends Service Committee, Circle of Peace, Creative Responses to Conflict, the Global Resources Committee, and the Michigan Institute for Nonviolence. The series includes administrative records, correspondence, events materials, publications, and other materials from the various groups.
  - American Friends Service Committee 1972-1992
    - Administrative Records 1972-1992 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1975-1981 (Box 2)
    - Events 1974-1980 (Box 2)
    - Financial Records 1975-1981 (Box 2)
  - Central America Working Group 1981-1989 (Box 2)
  - Circle of Peace 1993-2002
    - Administrative Records 1997-2001 (Box 2)
    - Educational Materials and Songs circa 1993-1998 (Box 2)
      (includes cassette tape)
    - Events 1997-2002 (Box 2)
  - Coalition for Local Reinvestment 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Creative Responses to Conflict 1989-1999
    - Administrative Records 1989-1998 (Box 2)
    - Events 1989-1999 (Box 2)
    - Presentation Materials 1989-1998 (Box 2)
  - Disarmament Working Group 1984-1988 (Box 2)
  - Global Resources Committee 1986-2008
    - Administrative Records 1993-2008 (Box 2)
    - Educational Materials 1989-1997
      - "Educating for Peace" 1997 (Box 2)
      - Peacemaker Slideshow 1988 (Box 2)
      - Teacher Resources 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Events 1986-2008
      - Arab World Workshop 1994 (Box 2)
      - Peace Education Week 1986-1994 (Box 2)
      - Peace Education Week 1995-2008 (Box 2)
    - Publications 1988-2005
      - Global Resources Newsletter 1991-1996 (Box 2)
      - Global Resources Newsletter 1997-2005 (Box 2)
      - Peace Calendars 1988-1994 (Box 2)
      - Peace Calendars 1995-2003 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Institute for Nonviolence 1971-1977
    - Administrative Records 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    - Events 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Financial Records 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Publications 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - Middle East Education Project 1990 (Box 3)
  - Peace Presence 1989 (Box 3)
  - South Africa Working Group 1986 (Box 3)
  - Toys Committee 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - YES (Youth Organization) 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Other Groups undated 2004 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series documents IGE events and activities and includes two photo albums (in folders) that cover the years 1980 to 1997. The series also contains a photograph of the late Walter Bergman, a Grand Rapids peace activist who participated in the civil rights movement and was beaten as a Freedom Rider in 1961.
  - Bergman, Walter undated (Box 3)
    (civil rights activist and Freedom Rider)
  - Photo album 1980-1990 (Box 3)
  - Photo album 1991-1997 (Box 3)
  - Wagbo Peace Center in East Jordan, MI 1995 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous undated 1992-1993 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series consists of seven volumes (one of which covers the Western Michigan American Friends Service Committee) and contain clippings, correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia from IGE events. The 1990-1992 volume covers anti-war activities relating to the first Persian Gulf War and the 1990-2005 volume contains news articles and letters to the editor regarding IGE members and activities.
  - 1974-1978 (Box 4)
    (material from the Western Michigan American Friends Service Committee)
  - 1980-1984, 1 volume (in 4 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1985-1989 (Box 4)
  - 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    (includes materials documenting opposition to the Persian Gulf War)
  - 1990-1996 (Box 5)
  - 1996-2000 (Box 5)
  - 1990-2005 (Box 5)